All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is קיי''ז Kuf
Yud Zayin 117, but we start on the משנה Mishna קט''ז ע''ב.
Kuf Tet Zayin Amud Bet.
We just had a whole discussion about saving כתבי קודש, Kitvei Kodesh,
scripture that's during a fire on שבת, Shabbat, and some
discussion around whether it's written in other languages, other types of specifics,
fascinating digression around ספרי מינים, Sifrei Minim, anyway we are back to
the issue about saving כתבי קודש Kitvei Kodesh on שבת, Shabbat, and
the משנה Mishna continues as follows: קט''ז ע''ב, Kuf Tet Zayin Amud
Bet, first wide line. מצילין תיק הספר עם הספר, Matzilin tik hasefer
im hasefer, while you're saving the actual ספר, Sefer, ספר תורה Sefer
Torah or other books of תנ''ך, Tanakh, you can save also the
container, the like the mantel, the container. ותיק תפילין עם התפילין, Vetik
tefillin im hatefillin, and implicitly you can also save תפילין, Tefillin, you
can also save their bag, their container. ואף על פי שיש בתוכן
מעות, Ve'af al pi she'yesh betokhan ma'ot, and not only that, not
only is it something that you're allowed to save and we're not
overly concerned that you'll come to put out a fire if we
let you save too much, but even if there's a מוקצה Muktzeh
problem, even if there's money in that bag. ולהיכן מצילין, Uleheikhan matzilin,
and now where can you bring them to, these things that you're
saving?
ולהיכן מצילין אותן למבוי שאינו מפולש, Uleheikhan matzilin otan lemavoi she'eino mefulash,
to a מבוי, Mavoi, a courtyard that is not open at both
ends. מפולש Mefulash means open at both ends, a thoroughfare. So presumably
we're allowing some rabbinic issue around carrying, we'll see in a minute
that there is some problem with this מבוי, Mavoi, it is not
totally permitted to carry through, but at least it is not open
at both ends, presumably it has three walls.
בן בתירה אומר, Ben Beteira omer, בן בתירה Ben Beteira says, אפילו
למפולש, Afillu lemefulash, even to a מבוי Mavoi that is open at
both ends, which is pretty shocking, that could be a real problem
of carrying, hopefully not biblical, but anyway, but certainly a more serious
issue, he even allows that. So right now we have explicitly what
is being allowed here in the משנה Mishna for ספרים Sefarim is
number one that you can take them to a courtyard that is
not fully permissible to be carried and the debate about how much.
Number two you can incidentally even move מוקצה Muktzeh in the process
of saving them. So those are two explicit things that are allowed
here for ספרים Sefarim and number three which is less explicit is,
and we'll see that more when we get to the next משנה
Mishna which contrasts it to saving food, that we either allow you
or we restrict how much you can save out of a concern
of coming to put out the fire. So that issue we will
look at a little bit more later, but the explicit things that
we're allowing here are to a courtyard that is not fully permissible
to be carried and the moving of the מוקצה. Muktzeh. Let's take
a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara sort of
focuses on the מוקצה Muktzeh issue first. Yes. בן בתירה, Ben Beteira,
who is he? He's a תנא. Tanna. What do you mean why
it's interesting that it calls him like the son without the first
name? I just haven't heard of him before.
Yeah, he is around.
I believe also בן בתירה Ben Beteira focuses significantly in the stories
where, if I'm remembering correctly, where there was a whole discussion actually
interestingly because the גמרא's Gemara about to introduce the whole issue about
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach being brought on שבת Shabbat in the famous
גמרא Gemara which speaks about when it was שבת Shabbos fell out
on ערב פסח Erev Pesach or ערב פסח Erev Pesach fell out
on שבת Shabbat and there was a whole question about what are
you allowed to do to, you know, bring the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach and, you
know, they had to basically get הלל Hillel to come and to
teach what, you know, he says that he has a tradition from
שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya ve'Avtalyon. Anyway, if I'm remembering that story, the בני
בתירה Bnei Beteira sort of are opposing הלל's Hillel teachings, like seeing
him as somewhat of an innovator from what I remember. It's either
that story or the story when רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai wanted to blow the שופר Shofar in יבנה Yavne after
the חורבן בית המקדש, Churban Beis HaMikdash, but anyway, but בני בתירה
Bnei Beteira certainly feature and בן בתירה Ben Beteira as well is
a תנא Tanna that appears from time to time. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says the following. תנו רבנן: Tenu rabbanan: ארבעה עשר
שחל להיות בשבת. Arba'ah asar shechal lihyot beShabbat.
So interesting, we weren't expecting this, let's see where the גמרא's Gemara
going with this. If the 14th of ניסן Nisan falls out on
שבת, Shabbat, so there's a whole issue about bringing the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach and you can do it because it's, this is the
one date to bring it, but then there's a how much are
you allowed to do on שבת Shabbat for the sake of bringing
the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So, שוחטו את הפסח, Shochato et hapesach,
מפשיטין את הפסח עד החזה, Mafshitin et hapesach ad hachazeh, דברי רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. Divrei Rabbi Yishmael beno shel
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the son of רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says you can flay it
until the chest, you from the legs up, you know, not from
the head down, from the legs up until the chest, and then
you're able to take out all of the innards, the אימורין, Emurim,
and put the אימורין Emurim on the מזבח Mizbe'ach because you're allowed
to, you offer up the אימורין Emurim on שבת Shabbat since you're
bringing the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת, Shabbat, but you cannot
flay it completely, which would be helpful for the meat because you're
not going to eat the meat until מוצאי שבת. Motzaei Shabbat. That's
what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, מפשיטין את
כולו. Mafshitin et kulo. No,
you can flay the entire פסח. Pesach. בשלמא Bishlama leRabbi Yishmael beno
shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, we understand רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael position,
דהאי עביד לצורך גבוה, Dehai avid letzorech gavo'ah,
you're doing what you need for God for the... bringing it on
the altar, and since you do that on שבת, Shabbat, that's allowed.
אלא רבנן מאי טעמא, Ella Rabbanan mai ta'ama, for the Rabbis why
is it allowed? Anything more is not needed to bring the innards
on the altar. It's needed for the meat, and that's not needed
for today, that's for tomorrow. So אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן דאמר קרא, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan
damar kra, because the verse says כל פעל השם למענהו, Kol pa'al
Hashem le-ma'anehu,
everything that God has done is for His sake, which is a
fascinating פסוק. pasuk. What does that have to do with anything? But
somehow it means that all of this is ultimately for God's sake
as well. I mean, you're bringing the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach because
it's a מצוה. mitzvah. The eating of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
at night will be a מצוה. mitzvah. So all of this is
in the context of bringing of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, and
therefore we don't sort of look at it, you know, microscopically to
distinguish between whether this is needed exactly for the מזבח mizbe'ach or
is this needed for the הדיוט. hedyot. It's all in the context
of bringing the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay. והכא מאי למענהו איכא?
Ve-hacha mai le-ma'anehu ikka?
What purpose is it serving? רב יוסף אמר כדי שלא יסריח, Rav
Yosef amar kedei shelo yasriach, so that the meat won't spoil. I
mean, and ultimately you are bringing the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach for
the sake of eating the meat. And by the way, more than,
I mean, we'll talk about this at length when we do פסחים,
Pesachim, but by other קרבנות, korbanot, the eating of the meat, when
it's done, whether by the כהנים Kohanim or the owners, is more
incidental. The עיקר קרבן ikkar korban is the sprinkling of the blood
or the throwing of the blood on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But by
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, the whole point of bringing the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach is in order so that you should be able to
do the אכילה achilah of the פסח Pesach at night. So the
fact that here you're allowed to do something even on שבת Shabbat
for the sake of eating the meat afterwards is particularly, you know,
the case by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach where it's brought for the
sake of being eaten. Okay. So therefore you are allowed to flay
it. That's the first explanation of the Rabbis. רבא אמר שלא יהא
קדשי שמים מוטלים כנבלה, Rava amar shelo yehei kodshei shamayim mutalim ke-nevelah,
that the things that are sanctified for God should not be cast,
you know, sort of like laying around like a נבלה, nevelah, like
an animal that just dropped dead. You know, it's just a, it's
just an unseemly way to have this carcass here with this half-flayed
skin. So it's much more about, if you almost would, the aesthetics,
the appropriateness of it, rather than actually preserving the meat. And that's
an interesting, that that alone is enough to allow you to continue
to flay it. I will tell you a, I don't know, somewhat
interesting parallel. We're going to pretty soon get up to a פרק
רבי אליעזר דמילה Perek Rabbi Eliezer de-milah that talks about doing a
ברית מילה Brit milah on שבת. Shabbat. And the גמרא Gemara there
says that if in the act of the ברית מילה, Brit milah,
before the מוהל mohel has completely sort of removed, you know, his
hand, he's still in the middle of doing what he's doing, even
if there are some like little pieces of skin that would not
prevent the מילה milah from being כשר, kosher, it would still be
כשר kosher even without removing them, if he's still in the middle
of the process he can continue to cut them on שבת. Shabbat.
Once he's stopped, he can't go back if they don't prevent it
from being כשר, kosher, but if he's in the middle of the
process he can continue. So somehow once we allow certain things on
שבת, Shabbat, we might at least under certain contexts allow them, you
know, even if the specific detail here is not ultimately necessary, since
it's in the larger process of something that is allowed on שבת.
Shabbat. So it's interesting here that רבא Rava is saying also even
not for the sake of eating the פסח, Pesach, just for the
sake that it should be appropriate, it shouldn't look inappropriate, we are
allowed to do that on שבת Shabbat according to the חכמים. Chakhamim.
So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What would be a difference between רבא's
Rava explanation and רב יוסף's Rav Yosef explanation? The one who emphasizes
the meat spoiling versus the one who emphasizes the whether it's unseemly
or not? So איכא בינייהו דמנח אפתורא דדהבא. ikka beinaihu de-manach aphtora
de-dahava. Let's say you have it on a gold table. So nobody
would say that looks like a נבלה. nevelah. That sort of counteracts
the fact that it's half-flayed is that you're treating it very respectfully,
you put it on a gold table. So that would not be
a problem according to רבא. Rava. It would still be a problem
according to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. If that's true, you wonder how
come it would ever be permissible according to רבא. Rava. Just put
it on a gold table, you solve the problem. אי נמי, i
nami, or another difference is יומא דאסתנא. yoma de-astana.
If it is a day of a very, like a certain type
of a wind, רש"י Rashi says a north wind, that keeps the
meat nice and cool so it doesn't spoil. Okay. So in that
type of a case it would not be a problem of it
spoiling, but it would still be a problem of whether it is
being treated appropriately. Okay. ורבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
האי כל פעל השם למענהו מאי עביד ליה? Ve-Rabbi Ishmael beno shel
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hai kol pa'al Hashem le-ma'anehu mai avid lei?
According to Rabbi Ishmael, what does he do with this פסוק? pasuk?
It's so funny, right? Again, who says that פסוק pasuk has anything
to do with a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at all? But okay,
that's the way the גמרא Gemara acts, it says, you know, sometimes
operates. It says what do you do about this value that we
do everything for the sake of God, and so maybe we should
allow, you know, even with more latitude, allow what you're doing here?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, he explains that in yes, giving
you a little latitude but not as much as רבא Rava and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef or not as much as the חכמים. Chakhamim.
מאי עביד ליה? mai avid lei? שלא יוציא אימורין קודם שיפשיט העור.
shelo yotzi imurin kodem she-yafshit ha-or. He allows you at least to
flay it until you can remove the innards. He doesn't tell you
cut straight through the skin and get to the inside and remove
the innards.
Now מאי טעמא mai ta'ama and why does flaying, is that helpful
for removing the innards? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב נתן. Amar Rav
Huna breih de-Rav Natan. משום נימי mishum nimi because again you remember
what you're שחטינג, shechting, you're שחטינג shechting a sheep or a goat.
So if you don't flay it first, then you take the innards
out and you've got all this woolly skin on the outside or
hairy skin that'll get into the innards and it'll make it icky,
which is a technical term. So anyway, so therefore he allowed it.
But the point is yes, he gives you latitude when you're specifically
doing something for the sake of the מזבח mizbeach to get out
the innards, then he gives you a little more latitude. But to
do other things just so it shouldn't look unseemly, just so the
meat should be more preserved, that he does not allow you on
שבת. Shabbat. Yes. Not only does that verse not only have no
evidence, no obvious relationship to קרבנות, korbanot, it's from כתובים Ketuvim and
so we have a verse from כתובים Ketuvim permitting something that would
be- I know, that always bothers you. Yes, you know, it's it's
it's more of like a גילוי מילתא, giluy miltza, let the rabbis
always have ways of saying it's just sort of ex- you know,
sort of like informing you of a general perspective and ultimately at
the end of the day, you know, פסח Pesach is דוחה שבת.
doche Shabbat. We don't- the verse in כתובים Ketuvim isn't telling us
it's דוחה שבת. doche Shabbat. We're just sort of trying to understand
what are the parameters of that and this is sort of revealing
to us a general- like a general approach about like a question
about like how much latitude, you know, you know, we generally have.
Okay, but yeah, there- it's- oh- there's always ways of saying it's
not directly teaching you הלכה, halacha, it's just revealing to us a
certain type of an approach. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Now what does any of this have to do with us? So
we're going to see in a minute. אמר רב אשי אמר מר
עוקבא: Amar Rav Ashi amar Mar Ukva: מאי הדרו ליה חברייא לרבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא? mai hadru lei chavrayia leRabbi Yochanan ben Beroka? What
do the colleagues, the rabbis
respond to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka who's you
know, what type of a proof would they bring to give- try
to argue for a little more latitude here for the קרבן פסח?
korban Pesach? So הכי קאמרי ליה, hachi ka'amreilei, this is what they
would say to him. אם מצילין תיק הספר עם הספר, Im matzilin
tik hasefer im hasefer, so this is what we were leading up
to because somehow this was- there was an- there was a tradition
that they would use our משנה, mishna, which gave a certain amount
of latitude for saving ספרי קודש sifrei kodesh on שבת Shabbat to
argue similarly by קרבן פסח korban Pesach on שבת. Shabbat. אם מצילין
תיק הספר עם הספר, Im matzilin tik hasefer im hasefer, if we
can save the- the- the container, the pouch of the קרבן- of
the- of the- ספר תורה sefer Torah or of the כתבי קודש
kisvei kodesh together with it on שבת, Shabbat, לא נפשוט את הפסח
מראשו? lo nafshit et hapesach meirosho? Should we not allow you to
flay the entire skin off the פסח? Pesach? So the גמרא Gemara
says: What? מי דמי? Mi dami? How can you compare then? התם
טלטול, Hasam tiltul, there at most we're talking about a moving thing,
מוקצה, muktzeh, maybe moving it into a courtyard that is not 100%
rabbinically allowed to be carried in, but you know some rabbinic problem.
Anyway right now we're focusing on מוקצה. muktzeh. הכא מלאכה, Hacha melacha,
you're flaying, right, that's a real מלאכה melacha on שבת Shabbat if
it were not for the override of the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב אשי: amar Rav Ashi: בתרתי
פליגי. bitartei pligi. Actually it's a double debate by the קרבן פסח.
korban Pesach. פליגי בטלטול, pligi bitiltul, number one they're debating a מוקצה
muktzeh issue and פליגי במלאכה, pligi bimelacha, and they're debating what we've
seen so far which is the מלאכה, melacha, the flaying. והכי קאמר
ליה, Vehachi ka'amar lei, and here's what they're saying to him. אם
מצילין תיק הספר עם הספר, Im matzilin tik hasefer im hasefer, if
you're allowed to save the covering of the ספר תורה sefer Torah,
together with the ספר תורה, sefer Torah? לא נטלטל עור אגב בשר?
lo nitaltel ora agav basar? Should we not be allowed to carry
the skin together with the meat? Meaning what? Meaning רש"י Rashi says
if the skin is still attached to the meat, how are you
allowed to carry the skin? The skin is not usable on שבת,
Shabbat, it's מוקצה. muktzeh.
תוספות Tosafot does not like that, that it's- we're assuming it's still
carried- it's still attached. תוספות Tosafot assumes let's even assume in some
case that somebody didn't listen whatever it was it did get flayed
completely. Okay, so there would still be a desire to pick up
the carcass using the skin, right, so you don't get the skin-
the actual flesh messy with your hands or your hands messy with
it, so anyway you're using and then it's very much as like
the תיק tik of the ספר sefer with the ספר. sefer. You're
using the skin as the- you know, the flayed flesh as a
container or as a way of transporting the actual meat. So presumably
they understood that רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka was
not only saying you can't flay it, but he was actually also
saying you cannot use the- the flayed skin to carry the קרבן
פסח. korban Pesach. And they said how is that any different than
our case by the ספר תורה? sefer Torah So the גמרא Gemara
says: top of קט"ז ע"א. kuf yud zayin amud alef. מי דמי?
Mi dami? One minute, how can you compare them?
התם נעשה בסיס לדבר המותר, Hasam na'asa basis ledavar hamutar, הכא נעשה
בסיס לדבר האסור. hacha na'asa basis ledavar ha'asur. One case it was
a בסיס לדבר המותר basis ledavar hamutar for something permissible, the container
of the ספר תורה sefer Torah was a base was a you
know something that supported a ספר תורה Sefer Torah, which was totally
not מוקצה. muktzeh. So the container isn't מוקצה muktzeh at all, I
mean what- what's the problem? Here the skin is a בסיס לדבר
האסור. basis ledavar ha'asur. What does it mean it's a בסיס לדבר
האסור? basis ledavar ha'asur? Because so according to רש"י Rashi because the
flesh isn't edible on שבת, Shabbat, it's raw. תוספות Tosafot says even
more than that, it's because the what do you call it the
when שבת Shabbat began the flesh was cont- was was you know
it was alive, right, the animal was still alive and therefore the
flesh of a live animal on שבת Shabbat is מוקצה. muktzeh. So
certainly when שבת Shabbos began it was all מוקצה. muktzeh. So it's
radically different. אלא הכי קאמר ליה. Ela hachi ka'amar lei. Okay, so
here's what they're saying to him here's- That's so funny, we had
this tradition that they made this argument by our משנה, Mishna, we're
trying to reinterpret the whole thing to explain how the משנה Mishna
was relevant. So let's take a look. אימא צולין תיקא של ספר
אימא ספר Ima tzolin tiksa shel sefer ima sefer ואף על פי
שיש בתוכו מעות. ve-af al pi she-yesh betocho ma'ot. But that's really
the חידוש chiddush of our משנה. Mishna. Not only that you can
carry out the container of the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah. but even
if it has money in it. So even though you're moving מוקצה
muktzah indirectly, and even though it was a בסיס basis for the
money because when שבת Shabbos began the money was in it, you're
allowed to move it on שבת. Shabbat. לא נטלת עור אגב בשר?
Lo nitata or agav basar? Shall we not allow you to also
move the the you know the skin, the hide together with the
meat? So even though there maybe the meat was מוקצה, muktzah, it's
no different than the money that was in the the container of
the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah So the גמרא Gemara says מי דמי?
Mi dami? How can you compare them? התם נעשה בסיס לדבר האסור
ולדבר המותר. Hatam na'aseh basis le-davar ha-asur u-le-davar ha-mutar. By the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah container, it's true that where there was money in
it, but there was also ספר תורה Sefer Torah. in it. So
it was a base, it was a container for something that was
permissible and forbidden. And something that is a בסיס basis for דבר
המותר davar ha-mutar and דבר האסור davar ha-asur does not have a
status of a בסיס. basis. It's not a problem. So at most
you have an issue of incidentally moving מוקצה, muktzah, and you're not
moving the money for the sake of the money, you're moving it
for the sake of the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah So there's really
no problem in our משנה. Mishna. הכא כולי נעשה בסיס לדבר האסור.
Hacha kulei na'aseh basis le-davar ha-asur. Here the entire skin is a
basis for the flesh which is a דבר האסור. davar ha-asur. So
again, you cannot make any comparison. Okay, אלא הכי קאמרי ליה. Ella
hachi kaamrei lei. Okay, here let's try again. אם הביא תיק שיש
בתוכו מעות מעלמא להציל בו ספר תורה. Im hevi tik she-yesh betocho
ma'ot me-alma le-hatzil bo Sefer Torah. Look, our משנה Mishna presumably, although
it's not in the משנה, Mishna, the גמרא Gemara is assuming the
same way you can take the ספר תורה Sefer Torah out with
its container even with money in it, let's say you didn't have
a container that was surrounding the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and you
had to run to I don't know you know run to a
side room that there was a ספר תורה Sefer Torah container and
in that side room the container of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
had money in it. Okay, so not that it started with a
container of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah plus money when שבת Shabbos
began, it was just a container with money. You took it and
you brought it to where the ספר תורה Sefer Torah was, you
put the ספר תורה Sefer Torah. in it and you took it
out. So the way that makes the case different is that when
שבת Shabbos began all that was in that container was money, not
also ספר תורה. Sefer Torah So it was only a בסיס לדבר
האסור. basis le-davar ha-asur. So somehow we're assuming that that's also permissible
although the משנה Mishna never described that case. But the גמרא Gemara
assumes it would be just as permissible. אם הביא תיק שיש בתוכו
מעות מעלמא, Im hevi tik she-yesh betocho ma'ot me-alma, if you can
bring a container that has money in it from somewhere else להציל
בו ספר תורה le-hatzil bo Sefer Torah to save a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah. even though that was only a בסיס לדבר האסור, basis
le-davar ha-asur, לא נטלת עור אגב בשר? lo nitata or agav basar?
Shall we not allow you to move the meat to you know
to move the skin together with the meat even though there it
is a בסיס לדבר האסור, basis le-davar ha-asur, but you're doing it
to protect the meat? So the same way here protect the ספר
תורה. Sefer Torah So now the גמרא Gemara says okay, but והיא
גופא מנלן? ve-hi gufa minalan? Whoever told you you could do that?
You could take a box that has money in it? אילימא דמידי
היכא דאית ביה לא שדי ליה. Ilema di-midi heicha de-it bei lo
shadei lei. If you say by the on the same principle that
if it had the ספר תורה Sefer Torah, in it with the
money we didn't demand that you that you throw the money out,
we allowed you to ignore the money and take the ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah אייתויי נמי מייתינן, aituyei nami maitinan, so by that same
argument by that same line of reasoning you can bring the box
with the money in it from somewhere else. So again there's a
big difference. מי דמי? Mi dami? התם אדהכי והכי נפלה דליכא, Hatam
ade-hachi ve-hachi nafla de-leika, הכא אדהכי והכי לישתייא. hacha ade-hachi ve-hachi lishtaiya.
So first of all you could say the biggest difference is in
one case it's a בסיס לדבר האסור basis le-davar ha-asur and the
other case it's a בסיס לדבר האסור ולדבר המותר, basis le-davar ha-asur
u-le-davar ha-mutar, exactly the point the גמרא Gemara was saying. Just because
we allow you to carry it when it had the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah. in it with the money doesn't mean we'll allow you
to carry it when it only had the money in it when
it really is a בסיס. basis. But the גמרא Gemara says תוספות,
Tosafot, but let's say we understand that the overriding concern here is
not a מוקצה muktzah concern. The overriding concern here is saving the
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah So presumably we would let you go to
a room and grab a box with money to save the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah even though it was a בסיס. basis. The גמרא
Gemara says that might be true but okay, but but then at
least as you're grabbing the box you should throw out the money
and then grab it when it's the ספר תורה Sefer Torah is
already in the box. You're not going to bother to take the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah, out, throw out the money and then whatever.
You just take the whole thing out. But even if you can
assume from our משנה Mishna that the overriding concern is saving the
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah. we'll let you grab the box with money
as you're running from the whatever the other room is with the
box, tip over the box as you're going to get the ספר
תורה. sefer Torah, So we don't really see think that that would
be a proof that you could actually do something if there's an
alternative. And therefore here that's why תוספות Tosafot says he has to
assume that the that the that the skin is totally flayed off
because here the argument would be if there's an alternative, there's some
other way that you could carry you know the skin or whatever
the meat without having to carry the skin presumably we would ask
you to do that. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא hacha
where were we?
אדהכי והכי אלא אמר
בר אבא אשי לעולם כדאמרן מעיקרא. ade-hachi ve-hachi ella amar bar Abba
Ashi le-olam ke-da-amran me-ikara. Really like we originally said, that for the...
of the skin and all of that. No, none of that. Forget
that.
It was like we said we tried to compare the carrying of
the of the of the תיק tik of the ספר sefer with
the flaying. Now what type of a comparison is that? כגון דלא
קפיד אלא אעור kegon d'lo kfid ella a-or
so actually because it's not a דאורייתא de'oraita here, it's a דרבנן.
derabbanan. Why is it a דרבנן? derabbanan? Yes, you're flaying it, but
flaying is only a מלאכה melacha if you want to preserve the
skin, you want to use the leather. Here you're just trying to
prevent it from causing the the meat to spoil or look unseemly.
So it's comparing the same way you forget about דרבננס derabbanans to
save the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, at least some דרבננס. derabbanans. מוקצה,
muktzeh, maybe some type of rabbinic carrying. Here too, we should forget
about the דרבננס derabbanans about flaying the the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
to preserve the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So you do understand some
rough comparison that the idea is you're preserving something holy and we're
a little bit overriding some דרבננס derabbanans to preserve something holy. Of
course there's very different types of דרבננס. derabbanans. But if we do
that for the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, we should do it for
the flaying of the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. And it's only rabbinic
because you don't want the skin. So the גמרא Gemara says והא
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו מודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות. veha
Abaye veRava d'amri tarvaihu modeh Rabbi Shimon bepsik reisha velo yamut.
Who cares? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that even if you're not
intending, if it's definitely going to happen, it's still a problem. And
here you still will definitely get the skin off. So what difference
does it make? Even if you're saying you're not interested in it
and you're like not מכוון? mechaven? Says גמרא Gemara says דשקיל ליה
בברזי. deshakil lei bevarzei. No,
what you do is that you cut it with a like types
of you know, you're flaying off tiny little pieces at a time.
You're not flaying off one big piece of skin. You know, so
it's like, you know, it's not like you're doing like a I'm
trying to think of an example. But anyway, like if you imagine
like a peeler, right? One would be like you did like of
I don't know of of a carrot. One would be like you
did the whole the whole layer. The other is like you're doing
tiny little pieces at a time, like you're scraping off little pieces.
So you can't use any of the skin. So it's not even
it's not דאורייתא de'oraita at all. There's no usable skin that's resulting.
So therefore it's only rabbinic. And some argument was if we allow
certain things for ספר תורה, sefer Torah. we should allow certain for
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Of course there's a million ways to make
distinctions even within that comparison. Not all דרבננס derabbanans are the same.
We didn't say we allow any דרבנן derabbanan for the ספר תורה.
sefer Torah We allowed within certain parameters. You know, and so who
knows whether קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is more of a reason to
overweigh, less of an over reason. Are the דרבננס derabbanans the same?
But at least that's the rough comparison. Charlie had a question. Yeah.
Usually the כהנים Kohanim get the hides of the קרבנות. Korbanot.
What happens to the hide of the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? Because
it doesn't stay in the the entire animal gets taken to people's
homes to be eaten. Yeah, the owner would get it. Sure. I
mean the owner gets the meat. Yeah. Okay. So anyway, that was
the first part. And what's fascinating also again is the sense that
you know, the proof that you're allowing a certain דרבנן derabbanan by
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach by the by the ספר תורה Sefer
Torah, is question is not so obvious. I mean, okay, there's money
in it, but as the גמרא Gemara says, it's a בסיס basis
for a דבר מותר davar mutar and a דבר אסור. davar assur.
What דרבנן derabbanan are you exactly allowing? I mean, you know, under
normal circumstances you'd be allowed to do something like that. You know,
so maybe the thing that wasn't in the משנה Mishnah that you
could take another box that has money in it. You know, and
even there it's not clear in the גמרא Gemara you wouldn't have
to throw the money out. The real bigger point is that you
can take it into a courtyard that is not totally permissible. And
that's the point that the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to
now. So let's take a look.
להיכן מצילין אותו? Le'heichan matzilin oto? To where can you bring the
these ספרי קודש? Sifrei Kodesh? So so there's a debate. The חכמים
Chachamim say it has to be אינו מפולש. eino mefulash. It can't
be open at both ends. And בן בתירא Ben Beteira says even
if it's open at both ends. So let's take a look. היכי
דמי
מפולש היכי דמי שאינו מפולש? Heichi dami mefulash heichi dami she'eino mefulash?
What does it mean open and what does it mean not open?
So אמר רב חסדא שלוש מחיצות ושני לחיים זהו מבוי שאינו מפולש.
Amar Rav Chisda shalosh mechitzot ushnei lechayayim zehu mavoi she'eino mefulash. So
it reads the משנה Mishnah much more restrictively than we would have
imagined. What's considered a מבוי mavoi that's not open? It
has שלוש מחיצות shalosh mechitzot and at the fourth wall it not
only has one לחי, lechi, it has שני לחיים. shnei lechayayim. Now
let me make this clear. What do you need rabbinically to carry
in a courtyard? You need it to have three walls and at
the opening wall, the unopened wall of the courtyard, you need it
to either have a קורה, korah, which is a beam, you know,
a horizontal beam that goes over at on the top. Or you
need one לחי, lechi, a post. Okay, plus you need to do
a שיתוף, shituf, you need to get everybody or an עירוב, eiruv,
you need to get everybody to join together in like, you know,
some food. Okay, so if you're saying that this is a מבוי
שאינו מפולש, mavoi she'eino mefulash,
you know, you would think that the point is okay, it means
that it doesn't have it has three walls, not two walls. But
presumably you would have imagined that it meant the fourth wall had
nothing. Okay, and מבוי מפולש mavoi mefulash sounds like two walls. So
the גמרא Gemara interestingly interprets this debate in the משנה Mishnah much
more restrictively and seems very anxious to assume that we would allow
you to carry. even into some type of a rabbinically problem, you
know, a courtyard that is a serious rabbinic problem. So what does
אינו מפולש eino mefulash mean? It means like three walls plus two
לחיי. lechayai. Okay, זה מבוי שאינו מפולש ze mavoi she-eino mefulash which
says the point is so then anyone you could be able to
carry anything in that type of a מבוי. mavoi. ג' מחיצות ולחי
אחד gimmel mechitzot ve-lechi echad and three walls with one לחי lechi
זה מבוי מפולש. ze mavoi mefulash. That's an open מבוי mavoi which
is quite shocking, that should be totally okay. So the גמרא Gemara
limits it a little bit. דתרוייהו אליבא דרבי אליעזר detravaihu aliba de-Rabbi
Eliezer and why is this called an open מבוי? mavoi? Because they're
arguing within the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. What does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say? דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה Mishna
in עירובין, Eruvin, הכשר מבוי, hechsher mavoi, what do you need to
carry in a
מבוי? mavoi? בית שמאי אומרים לחי וקורה, Beit Shammai omrim lechi ve-kora,
a vertical and a horizontal beam, ובית הלל אומרים או לחי או
קורה, u-Veit Hillel omrim o lechi o kora, which is how we
rule, either a לחי lechi which is a... which is a horizontal
beam or a post or a קורה kora which is a horizontal
beam. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
שני
לחיין, shenei lechayayim, two...
two לחי, lechi, one on each side of the open wall. Okay,
so now basically according to what רב חסדא Rav Chisda just said,
he said that so in principle you always need two לחיין. lechayayim.
So the first position says even when we let you save a
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah? it's only that the courtyard is 100% okay.
It has two לחיין. lechayayim. So there's not even a חידוש, chiddush,
big deal, so okay. And then the other position says I'm going
to be really liberal, I'm going to say that even if you
only have one לחי, lechi, even though רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer normally
needs two לחיין, lechayayim, I'm going to say even one לחי. lechi.
So the גמרא Gemara really wants to limit the cases in which
you would allow a, you know, a rabbinic overstep here for the
sake for this purpose. So רבא Rava is going to challenge this.
אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said to רב
חסדא, Rav Chisda, ג' מחיצות ולחי אחד מפולש קרית ליה? gimmel mechitzot
ve-lechi echad mefulash karyat lei? I don't get it. Number one, if
it has three מחיצות mechitzot and one לחי, lechi, even if you
normally need two לחיין, lechayayim, you would not call that an open-ended
מבוי, mavoi, a you know, you know, מפולש mefulash means open at
both ends, like it's wide open. So what? Because it has one
לחי lechi you're going to call it מפולש mefulash even if it's
not 100% okay? That's number one. ועוד ve-od and in addition, ולרבנן,
u-le-Rabanan, according to the rabbis that it has two לחיין, lechayayim, נצו
לתוכו הכי נמי דאסור? natzo le-tocho hachi nami de-asur? What's special about
ספר תורה? Sefer Torah, You can put anything into the courtyard. It's
not a special allowance by ספר תורה, Sefer Torah? right? אלא אמר
רבא, ela amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava says, שתי מחיצות ושני
לחיין זה מבוי שאינו מפולש. shetei mechitzot ve-shenei lechayayim ze mavoi she-eino
mefulash. Here's what we're talking about. You have only two מחיצות mechitzot
and you have one לחי lechi on each end. Now that sounds
crazy. Who says that's allowed at all? But we'll see in a
minute, this is according to another opinion, this is according to רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That would be a מבוי mavoi that's not מפולש.
mefulash. שתי מחיצות ולחי אחד זה מבוי מפולש, shetei mechitzot ve-lechi echad
ze mavoi mefulash, two מחיצות mechitzot and one לחי, lechi, that's an
open מבוי. mavoi. Now it makes sense to call it an open
מבוי, mavoi, but the question is that seems all of that seems
highly problematic. So let's see, he's going to explain. דתרוייהו אליבא דרבי
יהודה. detravaihu aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda. Both of these are going according to
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is like the opposite
extreme of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the
ברייתא, Beraita, יתר על כן אמר רבי יהודה. yeter al ken amar
Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda even said more than some other
position. מי שיש לו שני בתים בשני צדי רשות הרבים, mi she-yesh
lo shenei batim be-shenei tzedei reshut ha-rabim, let's say you have two
houses on two sides of a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. עושה לחי
מכאן ולחי מכאן, oseh lechi mi-kan ve-lechi mi-kan, you can make a
לחי lechi on either side on, you know, the north end of
your houses and one on the south end of your houses, או
קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן o kora mi-kan ve-kora mi-kan or a קורה
kora on the north end and the south end, ונושא ונותן באמצע
ve-nosei ve-noten ba-emtza and you can carry in the middle. So basically,
like, here's your street, right? You have one house here and one
house here, okay, and you've got a total thoroughfare... be careful here...
anyway, you got a total thoroughfare going here. It's open at both
ends. You put a קורה kora here and a קורה kora here,
or
a לחי lechi here and a לחי lechi here or a קורה
kora here and a קורה kora here, and even though the street
is open at both ends, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's
like you have four walls and you can carry in this space
in the רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim in the middle. Pretty radical position,
you know? You could imagine saying that that's a דאורייתא de-oraita רשות
הרבים reshut ha-rabim if it only has two real walls. Okay, but
that's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position that two walls with a לחי
lechi on each end or a קורה kora on each end is
okay. ואמרו לו, ve-amru lo, so the rabbis said back to him,
where was he... אין מערבין רשות הרבים בכך. ein me'arvin reshut ha-rabim
be-kach. I'm sorry, that does not make... that is not an עירוב
eruv on a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim if you only have two
real walls. So, but what does basically רבא Rava say? He's saying
look, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that actually two walls with a
לחי lechi on each side is enough. So when we say a
מבוי שאינו מפולש, mavoi she-eino mefulash, that would be that type of
a case. And a מבוי מפולש mavoi mefulash would be you only
have like one לחי, lechi, you know, or one קורה kora on
one side. You don't have them on both sides. Now you can
naturally say why it's called מפולש, mefulash, it's open-ended on both... the
language of מפולש mefulash is very appropriate. Okay, so that if that
was pushing him the language of מפולש, mefulash, you understand why he's
describing the case this way. But אביי Abaye still isn't happy. אמר
ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, לדידך נמי, le-didach
nami, fine,
I get the language of מפולש, mefulash, but according to the rabbis
that אינו מפולש eino mefulash means that you've got a קורה kora
on each side or a לחי lechi on each side, so if
that's all you need according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and we're
within רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so... לרבנן עד שתהא בו אכילה ושתיה,
lerabanan ad shetehei bo achilah u'shtiya, you're back to your old question:
why is it limited to a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah? Now you've
solved the language of מפלש, mefalash, but but if that's sufficient for
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, one on each side, why are you limited
to a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah. Now that question is so obvious
תוספות Tosafot says that רבא Rava is probably assuming that even when
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that's sufficient, maybe he means it's sufficient
biblically. It's not a hundred percent obvious that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say that's all you need rabbinically. So but so he assumes
that there's still a חידוש chiddush that you're allowed that that's sufficient
even rabbinically for a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah, But we're still back,
אביי Abaye doesn't like it because it's clear and again notice what's
so surprising, right? We read the משנה, mishna, we assume that we're
making some you know we're making some allowances for ספרי תורה, sifrei
Torah, for ספרי קודש, sifrei kodesh, and we're letting you do some
form of rabbinic carrying into the courtyard. The גמרא Gemara is really
resisting that surprisingly, really pushing back and trying to explain that what
you're allowed to do has to be a hundred percent kosher. But
of course then the question is so then why is it only
being said by ספרי תורה? sifrei Torah? So they ask, I mean
that's what they asked but again the idea that it's pushing on
this משנה mishna to limit it so radically is quite surprising. So
let's see where the גמרא Gemara ends up. אלא אמר רב אשי,
Ella amar Rav Ashi, so says רב אשי, Rav Ashi, שלש מחיצות
ולחי אחד זה מבוי שאינו מפלש. shalosh mechitzot u'lechi echad zeh mavoi
she'eino mefalash. Three מחיצות mechitzot with one לחי, lechi, that's a מבוי
mavoi that's אינו מפלש. eino mefalash. Right, that makes sense, that's maybe
normally what you would require. שלש מחיצות בלא לחי, shalosh mechitzot belo
lechi, however if there's no לחי lechi at all, זה מבוי המפלש,
zeh mavoi hamefalash, that's an open-ended מבוי. mavoi. ואפילו לרבי אליעזר, ve'afilu
le'Rabbi Eliezer, so let me so this is within רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. So here's the basic idea: רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer normally requires
three walls and two לחיים. lechayayim. So what is the allowance? So
according to the חכמים chachamim the allowance is even if it only
has one לחי. lechi. That's the big allowance, okay? Three walls, one
לחי, lechi, normally we require two. For ספרי קודש sifrei kodesh we'll
allow one. So it's אינו מפלש eino mefalash because it's got basically
four walls but it's not a hundred percent because it doesn't have
two לחיים. lechayayim. And then the other position is even מפלש, mefalash,
מפלש mefalash means nothing on the third end. Not מפלש mefalash on
both ends but I mean nothing on the fourth end, nothing on
the fourth end. But all that in either case it's got three
real walls. The only חידוש chiddush is that we have rather than
the two required לחיים lechayayim we've either one or zero.
ואפילו רבי אליעזר דאמר בעינן לחיים, ve'afilu Rabbi Eliezer de'amar ba'inan lechayayim,
even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says normally you need two לחיים. lechayayim.
הני מילי, hanei mili, that when is that true? לאוכלין ומשקין, le'ochlin
u'mashkin, that's for normal carrying. אבל לספר תורה, aval le'Sefer Torah, but
when it's coming special allowance to save a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah.
בחד לחי סגי, be'chad lechi sagi, one is enough. So again as
opposed to what I think we would have naturally said which is
the standard is three walls and one לחי. lechi. So I mean
my guess would have been reading that משנה mishna that according to
the חכמים chachamim even if there's no לחי. lechi. And according to
the position of who says בן בתירה Ben Beteira says מבוי מפלש
mavoi mefalash who knows maybe only two walls. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
want to go that far. It wants to assume that בן בתירה
Ben Beteira is only himself gonna demand three walls. It's hard if
you're not רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it's hard to imagine how you
would ever allow carrying without three walls. So even בן בתירה Ben
Beteira is gonna demand three walls and therefore what's how do you
what's the debate? So the debate is one לחי lechi or zero
לחיים lechayayim but everybody says three walls, very much limiting the cases
even for ספר תורה. Sefer Torah? So it's quite fascinating what do
we really allow for ספר תורה? sefer Torah Carrying the thing with
money so what? It was טלטול מן הצד, tiltul min hatzad, it
was בסיס לדבר מותר ולדבר אסור, basis ledavar mutar u'ledavar assur, that's
not a חידוש. chiddush. Carrying into a courtyard most what we've done
is allowed it when it had one fewer לחי lechi than it
required or maybe has no לחיים lechayayim but it has three walls.
We haven't allowed all that much. So the question is how much
is very much just basically allowing me to save anything forgetting carrying
and מוקצה muktzeh and whatever part of a special חידוש chiddush because
of a concern that once you allow me to start saving things
I might get too anxious and I might start putting out the
fire. And that we're going to see as we continue now to
discuss the issue about saving food and the rabbis trying on the
one hand if we tell you you can't save anything then you'll
also get anxious and you'll start putting out the fire, if we
tell you you can save too much then you'll get carried away
and trying to like strike this balance. So let's take a look
now at the next משנה mishna as we move from ספרי קודש
sifrei kodesh to food. מצילין
מזון שלש סעודות הראוי לאדם לאדם הראוי לבהמה לבהמה. matzilin mazon shalosh
se'udot haraui leadam leadam haraui lebehemah lebehemah. You can save the food
for three meals and by the way I should say that with
this we'll get into a nice whole discussion about eating שלש סעודות
shalosh se'udot on שבת, Shabbat, okay, the idea that there's three meals
because normally the assumption would be two meals. You can save food
for three meals, human food you can save for a person and
animal food for animals, okay כיצד keitzad how is this so? So
you can save you know you know you can save food for
the people and you can also save food for the animals up
to three meals. כיצד keitzad now what does it mean three meals?
It depends. נפלה דליקה בלילי שבת, naflah deleikah beleilei Shabbat, if the
fire came out you know sort of fell down you know broke
out on Friday night, מצילין מזון שלש סעודות matzilin mazon shalosh se'udot
then three
meals. בשחרית... beshacharit... Then מזון ב' סעודות mazon bais seudos only two
meals you can save. במנחה B'mincha if it broke out at Mincha
time then מזון סעודה אחת mazon seuda achas you can only save
for one meal because you only have one meal left to eat
assuming again that מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos even if your food burned
at least you'll be able to prepare new food once שבת Shabbos
is over. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says לעולם מצילים מזון שלוש סעודות. le'olam matzilin mazon shalosh seudos. I
don't care when it broke out. Since people eat three meals on
שבת Shabbos you can always save three meals. That's considered שבת Shabbos
food, three meals no matter what time it happens on שבת. Shabbos.
Okay and we're going to then have to also see what type
of a courtyard can you save this to and is that going
to be you know the same parameters as a ספר תורה sefer
Torah or different. Okay so let's take a
look. Just want to see one thing, one minute.
Right so okay fine so now the גמרא Gemara says like this
מכדי michdi let's take a look. בהיתירא קטרח. b'heteira katrach. You are
doing something that's totally permissible. What that means is there's no מוקצה,
muktzah, it's food and as רש"י Rashi points out as opposed to
what we just got through saying by a ספר תורה sefer Torah
that we allow it into a courtyard that's not 100% kosher, maybe
it has one לחי lechi instead of two or zero instead of
one, by the food you're actually talking about saving it into a
courtyard that is 100% kosher. So the only concern is, so we
don't even know what the concern is if it's food and the
courtyard is 100% kosher like we're going to see in the next
משנה, Mishna, why should we limit you at all? Why can't you
save as much food as you want? So ניציל טפי? nitzil tfei?
Let's save as much as you want. So אמר רבא Amar Rava
ומתוך umitoch and here's the idea that when it's a fire we
have to put certain restrictions on it. מתוך שאדם בהול על ממונו
mitoch she'adam bahul al mamono because you're so anxious you're so feeling
like rushed or pressured about your money that's being destroyed אי שרית
ליה ei sharis lei if you overly allow אתי לכבויי asi l'chabbuyei
he'll get so focused on getting everything out of the house he'll
come to put out the fire. So if you limit it, grab
three סעודות seudos and run out then you know then that will
hopefully prevent him from from from being unwittingly
or from you know losing his his
his attention to the fact that it's שבת Shabbos and putting out
the fire. So here you see on the one hand we might
make certain allowances like by the ספר תורה we might allow you
know bringing into a courtyard that's not 100% kosher and on the
other hand we make certain restrictions like by the food even if
the courtyard is 100% kosher we make certain restrictions because we don't
want you to get too focused on saving everything and come to
put out the fire. I will repeat what I said on שבת
Shabbos which is is that you know להלכה lehalacha we are much
more liberal in terms of putting out fires on שבת Shabbos because
of the סכנה sakana aspects of it which raises questions like why
weren't those concerns at the time of the גמרא Gemara but never,
I don't know the answer to that you know maybe I don't
know maybe maybe in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the Romans had a
whole fire department. What did they do, the Romans? Did they have
like a whole Israel barely has a fire department to begin with.
What? Because of the stone houses. Yes stone houses and dirt floors
there's not a lot that'll burn. Oh that's an interesting perspective. The
stone houses. Ah and in אשכנז Ashkenaz maybe it was much more
wooden types of oh that's a good wooden houses oh that's a
good perspective. Ah okay so that's helpful in understanding this. Okay so
anyway okay so all
right so anyway so you see here even on the one hand
we allow certain things on the other hand we have to restrict
how much you do out of a concern you'll come to put
it out. אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye so אביי Abaye says
אלא הא דתניא ela ha detanya that which we learned in a
ברייתא braita נשברה לו חבית בראש גגו nishbera lo chavis b'rosh gago
your barrel filled with wine broke on your roof. What do you
do on שבת? Shabbos? מביא כלי ומניח תחתיה meivi kli u'maniach tachteha
you can take a vessel and put it underneath it to catch
all the wine that's spilling out ובלבד שלא יביא כלי אחר ויקלוט
u'vilvad shelo yavi kli acher v'yiklot
don't start taking another vessel
and like you know sort of רש"י Rashi says ויקלוט v'yiklot means
if like the wine is like dripping you know sort of having
it there to catch the catch the drip or כלי אחר ויצרף
kli acher v'yitzaref or another vessel so that if it's like spilling
like it's puddled on the roof and you put this vessel at
the edge of the roof and it sort of you know it
sort of streams in and gets caught. You can put a vessel
underneath the barrel but not something that looks like it's an ongoing
process of salvaging the wine. Right it's a one-time thing you put
a vessel underneath the barrel and you try to save the wine
that's spilling out. But something like holding something to catch the drip
or you know bringing vessels that are like an ongoing flow an
ongoing salvage operation that not. So this isn't a fire and you're
not doing anything that's a biblical problem that's even a rabbinic problem.
What's the issue? So he says מאי גזירה איכא mai gezeira ika
what type of גזירה gezeira is there? Why you know it seems
similar to the fire idea limiting what we're allowed to do but
what's the concern? So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי גזירה שמא
יביא כלי דרך רשות הרבים hacha nami gezeira shema yavi kli derech
reshus harabbim הכא נמי גזירה שמא יביא כלי דרך רשות הרבים hacha
nami gezeira shema yavi kli derech reshus harabbim you're so focused on
a whole salvage operation you'll bring a vessel through רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim to come and do it and that's the concern. So but
it is interesting pointing out this parallel of not being overly engaged
in a salvage operation. There are some there are concerns that will
come out of it. גופא. Gufa. Now let's look at this case
itself. נשברה לו חבית בראש גגו nishbera lo chavis b'rosh gago your
barrel breaks on the top of... roof מביא כלי ומניח תחתיו ובלבד
שלא יביא כלי אחר ויקלוט כלי אחר ויצרף. Mavi kli u'maniach tachtav
u'belvad she'lo yavi kli acher v'yiklot kli acher v'yitzaref. So okay, you
can put a vessel underneath it, but don't start trying to catch
the drip or the flowing off the roof. נזדמנו לו אורחים, Nizdamnu
lo orchim, now let's say what happens is that all of a
sudden some guests knock at your door and you need some wine.
So, now you need wine. מביא כלי אחר וקולט כלי אחר מצרף,
Mevi kli acher v'kolet kli acher mitzaref, then you can get these
vessels because then you're doing it to get wine for your guests.
You're not doing it like, at least that's the ostensibly why you're
doing it, not doing it to salvage the wine and involve you
don't involve in a salvage operation. ולא יקלוט V'lo yiklot but don't
first gather ואחר כך יזמין v'acharkach yazmin and then invite your guests.
אלא יזמין ואחר כך יקלוט, Ella yazmin v'acharkach yiklot,
first invite your guests and then do it. Okay, fine, I'll first
invite my guests. But now that my wine is spilling, now's a
good time to invite guests. So it says no, ואין מערימין בכך.
v'ein maarimin be'kach.
You cannot sort of scheme about this. Don't invite guests as a
means, yeah,
but don't do it with that motivation. Okay, now by the way,
this whole idea of הערמה ha'arama is a discussion that comes up
in the גמרא Gemara and it comes up we do it like
selling your חמץ chametz for פסח, Pesach, selling the ear of a
בכור bechor to a non-Jew so that you don't have to give
בכור. bechor. So the whole idea of הערמה ha'arama in הלכה halacha
is an important topic. When do we sort of encourage or turn
a blind eye to sort of these schemes to get out of
these issues? So this says you don't scheme, but now רבי יוסי
בר יהודה אומר מערימין—you're Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda omer maarimin allowed to
scheme, not a problem. Look, in the end of the day, it's
only like some type of a concern that maybe you'll come to
do this and this type of an issue we allow you to
do that to salvage your wine. Okay, so now this issue of
can you scheme, right, it's interesting some places the גמרא Gemara has
this direct discussion of when do we allow you to do these
types of schemes. So the גמרא's Gemara going to compare it to
another debate. לימא בפלוגתא דרבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע
קמיפלגי—maybe Leima bi'pligta d'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Yehoshua kamifligi this is the same
debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. דתניא,
De'tanya, as we learned in a ברייתא, braitisa, אותו ואת בנו שנפלו
לבור
ביום טוב—and Oso v'es bno she'naflu l'bor b'yom tov a mother and
child cow or sheep fell into a pit. Now, if it was
only one or two different animals, you could save them both because
maybe you'll שחט shecht them both on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But
here you can't שחט shecht both of them on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. You can't שחט shecht אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es bno.
So what do you do? רבי אליעזר אומר מעלה את הראשון על
מנת לשחטו—you Rabbi Eliezer omer ma'aleh es harishon al menat l'shochto can
pull up the first one for the purpose of slaughtering it and
then והשני, v'hasheini, but once the first one is up there's no
justification for bringing up the second one.
והשני עושה לו פרנסה במקומו—you V'hasheini oseh lo parnasa bimkomo can lower
down food to where it is in its place but you cannot
raise it up בשביל שלא ימות bishvil she'lo yamut so it won't
die. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua אומר—רבי יהושע says, no, I got the
solution. מעלה את הראשון על מנת לשחטו—you Ma'aleh es harishon al menat
l'shochto bring up the first one, you say I'm going to שחט
shecht the first one ואינו שוחטו, v'eino shochto, then as soon as
it gets up to the top of the pit you say you
know what, I don't like this one so much. Okay, I've decided
I don't want to שחט shecht it, I want the one that's
at the bottom of the pit and then ומערים ומעלה את השני—you
u'ma'arim u'ma'aleh es hasheini can scheme, you can trick and then you'll
have you get an excuse to say you changed your mind and
bring the second one up once the first one is already up
and out of the picture. רצה זה שוחט רצה זה שוחט, Ratzah
zeh shochet ratzah zeh shochet, and now you can שחט shecht either
one. He's even going so far to say you can change your
mind back. After the second one is up, you can say I
changed my mind back, I'm going to go to the first one.
You might have thought if he allows the scheme it's only if
you carry through with it and שחט shecht the second one, but
he even goes so far to say once you've allowed the second
one up, now you can change your mind back to the first
one. So he really allows this whole little scheme in order to
do this. So it sounds like it's the same debate whether we
allow various types of schemes for at least for rabbinic issues.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, ממי, mimai, who tells you that
these are the exact same case? דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי
אליעזר התם—maybe Dilma ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer hasam when רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says I don't like you to do this scheme,
that's because דאפשר בפרנסה, d'efshar b'parnasa, there's a way that you won't
lose anything, you'll lower the food down to the
animal. So therefore he doesn't like the scheme because there's a reasonable
alternative. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, but here דלא אפשר, d'lo efshar, where
the wine is going to waste, so there's no alternative. So maybe
לא, lo, he would not have his objection. So maybe if the
thing is really going to waste he would allow you to scheme.
ועד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהושע התם, V'ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi
Yehoshua hasam, or the reverse, when does רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua allow
you to scheme by the animals? משום דאיכא צער בעלי חיים, Mishum
d'ika tza'ar ba'alei chayim, because there's another thing. It's not just to
help you not have a monetary loss. There's an animal at the
bottom of the well, there's צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. אבל
הכא, Aval hacha, but here with the wine דליכא צער בעלי חיים,
d'leka tza'ar ba'alei chayim, although the wine is going to waste, but
you don't have צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. לא, lo, he
would not allow the scheme. So sometimes we do, sometimes we don't,
but there are different types of things to consider in terms of
are there alternatives, what other factors are there? And therefore even though
there is debate by different תנאים tana'im at different times, you cannot
assume that somebody always takes one position on the matter. Okay, so
that's the idea of another salvage operation which is a rabbinic concern
and they allow a possibly a certain amount of scheming about inviting
guests. We're going to see another way also that they allowed a
certain amount of latitude by salvaging the food by the burning fire
as well about getting other people. people involved. Okay, so within this
rabbinic restriction there are there's a certain amount of latitude. Now we
continue. תנו רבנן: Tanna Rabbanan:
הציפה נקייה, Hitzeipa nikiya, if you first
saved fine bread, bread of a fine flour, אין מציפין פת הדראה,
ein matzipin pat hadraah, you cannot afterwards save bran bread because once
you have your nice bread who would eat bran bread?
אבל פת הדראה, Aval pat hadraah, however, if you first save bran
bread, then you could מציפין נקייה, matzipin nikiya, you could say, yeah,
I saved enough bread for three meals, but it's this bran bread
and I'd really like the fine flour bread and you can similarly
go back and save better food. Okay, food ומצילין מיום הכפורים לשבת.
u'matzilin miyom hakippurim l'shabbat. Now, let's say a fire breaks out on
Yom Kippur. You can't eat on Yom Kippur. You can nevertheless save
enough food for Shabbat if Shabbat is the next day. Again, this
was the time when they could have Shabbat and Yom Kippur back
to back. So if Yom Kippur was Friday, you can save for
Shabbat. Okay, so that's legitimate because you won't have an opportunity to
prepare the food for Shabbat and הכנה hachana isn't an issue. We
discussed הכנה hachana before from Yom Kippur to Shabbat. That's legitimate.
אבל לא משבת ליום הכפורים, Aval lo mishabbat l'yom hakippurim, but if
it's Shabbat, you can't save food for Yom Kippur because you can't
eat on Yom Kippur and for מוצאי יום הכפורים Motzaei Yom Kippur
you'll have time to prepare.
ואין צריך לומר משבת ליום טוב, Ve'ein tzarich lomar mishabbat l'yom tov,
you certainly can't save from Shabbat to Yom Tov because Yom Tov
you can prepare food and Shabbat can't prepare for Yom
Tov. ולא משבת לשבת הבאה, Velo mishabbat l'shabbat habaah, and not from
one Shabbat to the next Shabbat, a week later, because you have
six days in between to prepare your food. But you can save
on Yom Tov for Shabbat, again, because you won't have a chance
to prepare food on Shabbat and Yom Tov can
can be מכין לשבת. mechin l'shabbat. Okay, so that's that. Now, I
just want to look, show you a short תוספות. Tosafot. אבל לא
משבת ליום הכפורים, Aval lo mishabbat l'yom hakippurim, he says פירש בקונטרס
למוצאי יום הכפורים. Pirush b'Kuntress l'Motzaei Yom Kippur. What does that mean?
Why would I think you're saving for Yom Kippur? You can't eat
on Yom Kippur. No, the question was, should you save for מוצאי
יום הכפורים? Motzaei Yom Kippur? Because you won't have time to prepare
food, you want to get right into eating right afterwards. ואם תאמר,
Ve'im tomar, תוספות Tosafot says, פשיטא דחול גמור הוא, peshita d'chol gamur
hu, of course, it's a weekday. Shabbat can't prepare for a weekday.
ומה ישנא משבת למוצאי שבת, U'mai shna mishabbat l'motzaei Shabbat, why would
I think that that would be allowed? ויש לומר דמצוה לאכול במוצאי
יום הכפורים Ve'yesh lomar d'mitzvah l'echol b'motzaei yom hakippurim כדי לאפישי לאל.
kidei l'hafishi l'el. There's a mitzvah to eat by Yom Kippur when
Yom Kippur gets out right afterwards, so I might have thought that
that is enough of a justification to save from Shabbat to מוצאי
יום הכפורים. Motzaei Yom Kippur. Okay. ועוד לפי שנתענו, Ve'od lefi shehitunu,
because they fasted, מותר יותר, mutar yoter, it's even more permissible than
rather than delaying them getting into the eating. Okay. אי נמי, Inami,
he says, יום הכפורים עצמו, Yom Kippur atzmo, maybe you are saving
for Yom Kippur, but there are people who eat on Yom Kippur,
ולהאכיל לתינוקות, u'l'ha'achil l'tinokot, you have to feed the kids. Okay, so
anyway, that was the possibilities, and even if it somehow is a
legitimate reason, it goes back to the point before that Yom Kippur
may be considered Shabbat according to one opinion, but Shabbat cannot serve
Yom Kippur.
Okay. Now, last narrow line, תנו רבנן. Tanna Rabbanan. שכח
פת בתנור וקדש עליו היום. Shachach pat b'tanur vekiddesh alav hayom. So,
you left your bread in the oven and it became Shabbat. Now,
rabbinically you are not allowed to take bread out of an oven.
That's baking, רדיית הפת, rediyat hapat, the lowering of the bread, removing
the bread of the oven is called a חכמה, chachma, a type
of a skilled labor, it's not a מלאכה. melacha. You're not allowed
to do it on Shabbat. Okay. Fine. But you actually forgot and
now it's Shabbat, and if you don't take your bread out, you're
not going to have food for Shabbat, you're not going to have
bread for Shabbat. Do we allow you to override this rabbinic restriction
of removing bread for the sake of
salvaging meals on Shabbat? Now again, our Mishna remember did not allow
an override of a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, it just said that we're allowed
to do it and we won't be afraid you'll come to put
out the fire. Here there's a clear איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan to
do this, and if we let you do this to save three
meals, you could understand that that's opening up
this huge, huge gate, floodgates, oh well, if you left bread in
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat you can take off three meals' worth, right?
So there goes the restriction of at least to some degree of
removing bread on Shabbat. So let's take a look. שכח פת בתנור
וקדש עליו היום. Shachach pat b'tanur vekiddesh alav hayom. You forgot bread
in the oven and then it became Shabbat. מצילין מזון שלש סעודות.
Matzilin mazon shalosh seudot. You actually are allowed to save which is
quite shocking, much further than the Mishna went, you're actually allowed to
go against this דרבנן d'rabbanan and salvage three סעודות seudot from the
bread that is baking. ואומר לאחרים בואו והצילו לכם. Ve'omer l'acherim bo'u
vehitzilu lachem. And you can tell the other people, anybody who wants
three free loaves of bread to anybody who wants, and everybody comes
and saves for themselves three loaves of bread so it doesn't all
go to waste or three meals' worth of bread.
Okay. וכשהוא רודה, Ukeshu rodeh, now when you are removing the bread,
לא ירדה במרדיא, lo yirdeh b'mardeia, don't use the
classic shovel, the classic thing that was used to remove bread. Don't
use the normal vessel. אלא בסכין, Ela b'sakin, use a knife. I
hope the oven is no longer, I don't know how you do
it without burning yourself, but anyway you do it with like a
שינוי. shinui. Don't do it the normal type of removal because obviously
there's a generally an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan to remove bread on
Shabbat, certainly in the normal way. So the גמרא gemara says, איני?
eini? Is it really true that you have to do a שינוי?
shinuy? ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, ve-tana d'bei rebbi yishmael, we taught in
the house of רבי ישמעאל, rebbi yishmael, לא תעשה כל מלאכה, lo
sa'aseh kol melacha, do not do any מלאכה, melacha, but only מלאכה
melacha is forbidden. יצאת תקיעת שופר ורדיית הפת, yatzat tki'as shofar u-rediyas
hapas, things like blowing the שופר shofar or taking bread out of
the oven, don't be confused. Those are not מלאכות. melachos. Those are
not biblically forbidden. שהיא חכמה ואינה מלאכה, she-hi chochma ve-eina melacha, it's
a skill that's not a מלאכה. melacha. So therefore this whole thing
is rabbinic. So what's quite fascinating is the גמרא gemara saying why
do you have to use a knife, the whole thing is just
rabbinic, go ahead and do it normally. And the גמרא gemara says
no, nevertheless, כמה דאפשר לשנויי משנינן, kama d'efshar lishnuyei meshaninan, as it's
possible to do it with a שינוי shinuy we do it with
a שינוי. shinuy. Now again, that seems obvious and it's quite fascinating
that the גמרא gemara even thought that you could do it the
normal way because again, as opposed to the משנה, mishnah, the משנה
mishnah does not let you violate a דרבנן. d'rabonon. The משנה mishnah
actually is talking about a rabbinic restriction, you're doing nothing wrong, and
the rabbis say don't save more than three סעודות, seudos, we're afraid
that you'll come to put out a fire. Here they're actually violating
a rabbinic restriction of taking the bread out, if we let you
do this, you know, that might open up this like I said,
like the floodgates, and nevertheless we do let you do it. So
it makes a lot of sense that we'll only do it with
something like a שינוי. shinuy. So it's quite fascinating that the גמרא
gemara thinks that we might actually like you know be very liberal
in terms of this, there is not a precedent to that in
the משנה. mishnah. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara continues. אמר רב
חסדא, amar rav chisda, now we get from this idea of saving
and salvaging, and particularly salvaging food on שבת, shabbos, to a discussion
about eating on שבת. shabbos. So let's take a look. אמר רב
חסדא, amar rav chisda, לעולם ישכים אדם להוצאת שבת, l'olam yashkim adam
l'hotza'as shabbos, a person should always rise up early meaning like make
an extra effort to spend money for שבת, shabbos, particularly for the
food of שבת, shabbos, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as the פסוק posuk says, והיה
ביום הששי והכינו את אשר יביאו, v'haya bayom hashishi ve-hachinu es asher
yavi'u, and it was on the sixth day they prepared what they
would you know that that they would bring, אלתר, altar, immediately, as
soon as they woke up Friday morning they started getting the food
ready for שבת. shabbos. Okay, so that's what it means the first
thing you do Friday morning you should start you know going shopping
and getting ready for שבת. shabbos. אמר רבי אבא, amar rebbi abba,
בשבת חייב אדם לבצוע על שתי ככרות. be-shabbos chayav adam livtzoa al
shtei chikaros.
On שבת shabbos here's the idea of לחם משנה. lechem mishneh. Okay,
on it starts with a statement of רבי אבא, rebbi abba, it's
not in a משנה mishnah anywhere, it starts with this statement that
on שבת shabbos you're obligated to break bread over two loaves, דכתיב,
de-chsiv, לחם משנה, lechem mishneh, by the מן, mann, it says that
two loaves fell on Friday. So therefore you have to use two
loaves on שבת. shabbos. אמר רב אשי, amar rav ashi, חזינא ליה
לרב כהנא, chazina lei le-rav kahana, so I saw רב כהנא, rav
kahana, דנקיט תרתי, di-nakit tartei, he took both loaves when he made
המוציא, hamotzi, he held both of them, ובצע חדא, u-vatza chada, but
he only broke one loaf, he didn't actually break both loaves of
bread, he only broke into one which is what a lot of
people do and they save the other loaf for the next day,
for you know for שבת shabbos morning. So אמר, amar, and he
explained
it, it says למיקט כתיב, liktot ksiv, so למיקט liktot to gather,
so I held the two loaves. I don't have to break into
the two loaves, I only have to hold the two loaves and
that's all that you have to do. רבי זירא, rebbi zeira, רבי
זירא הוה בצע אכולה שירותא. rebbi zeira hava vatza akula sheirusa. He
would break bread on every thing that he would
what do you call it on like on all the loaves on
everything that he would sort of begin the meal with. אמר ליה
רבינא לרב אשי. amar lei ravina l'rav ashi. So I'm sorry, and
רש"י rashi also says that what it also means is that he
would have a chunk of bread in front of him that would
be large enough for like the full full meal. Okay, so he'd
be בוצע botzei'a for the whole meal.
So you know so a huge he would take a huge slice
of bread. So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei ravina l'rav
ashi, so רבינא ravina said to רב אשי, rav ashi, ואמחזי כרעבתנותא,
v'amichzei k'ravtanusa, it seems like like gluttony that you have like this
huge chunk of bread in front of you.
אמר ליה, amar lei, כיון דכל יומא לא עביד, keivan d'chol yoma
lo avid, since that's not the normal way I do it, והאידנא
הוא דקא עביד, v'ha'idna hu d'ka avid, and I'm only doing it
now, לא מחזי כרעבתנותא, lo michzei k'ravtanusa, it does not look like
some type of a gluttony, it just looks like you know like
it's done for the כבוד שבת, kavod shabbos, that it's a very
you know lavish meal and I have all I have this big
piece of bread in front of me, so it's done for the
sake of כבוד שבת kavod shabbos and it does not look inappropriate.
רב אמי ורב אסי, rav ammi ve-rav assi, רב אמי ורב אסי
rav ammi ve-rav assi כי מטלו להו ריפתא דערובא, ki matlu lehu
rifta d'eiruva, there's another practice that we do, when
they would get the bread that was used for making an עירוב.
eiruv. Right, now here it means הוה להו hava lehu like an
עירוב חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, but for us we do this for עירוב
תבשילין, eiruv tavshilin, the food that was used for making an
עירוב. eiruv. שרו ליה, sharu lei, they would eat on it, they
would they would begin their meal with it. אמרי, amri, they would
say, they make המוציא hamotzi on it. הואיל ואתעביד בה חדא מצוה,
ho'il v'is'avid bah chada mitzvah, since one מצוה mitzvah was done with
it, it was used to make an עירוב, eiruv, ליתעביד בה מצוה
אחרינא, lis'avid bah mitzvah achrina, let's do another מצוה mitzvah with it,
and therefore they would use it presumably for their סעודה seuda for
שבת shabbos or at least they would make a point of eating
it for some meal and maybe specifically also for a שבת shabbos
meal to use it for another מצוה. mitzvah. And some people דווקא
davka have this practice of like using the עירוב eiruv food, you
know to eat it on יום טוב yom tov or to use
it for שלש סעודות shalosh seudos or maybe to use it for
like I don't know for an עונג שבת oneg shabbos or something.
Anyway, so there and it comes to this, so we'll continue with
this tomorrow. Anyway so therefore and it comes to this so we'll
continue with this tomorrow with a discussion about various מצוות mitzvos relating
to eating on שבת. Shabbat.